Six months ago, if you wanted a personal
AI agent, you just installed Open Claw.
Everybody did this and we saw a massive
amount of hype. Then, this June, Hermes
Agent passed it. It's now at over 224
billion tokens per day versus Open Claw
at 186 billion. So, which one should you
actually run today? Well, in this video,
I'm going to set up both on real servers
with real tokens that I paid for and I'm
going to run the exact same jobs through
each one so you can see how they differ
and which one is best for your use case.
Now, I'm not just going to tell you,
"Oh, yeah, you should use both." because
the reality here is that one is much
better than the other specifically at
certain set of tasks and we're going to
dive into that right now. So, let's
start by looking at a few numbers,
understand where these projects stand
and then we're going to get into all of
the specifics. Now, Open Claw is a much
more mature project. It was released in
November 2025 and has over 137 releases
at this time. It has a massive hub of
skills that you can install. At one
point, they had over 13,000 skills.
There was then a bunch of security
issues that purged it down to 3,300 and
now it's grown back up to 5,400 at the
time of recording this video. Compared
to Hermes Agent, this was released later
in February 2026. It only has 11
releases at least when I'm recording
this video and while it doesn't come
with a massive amount of skills out of
the box, it can build its own skills and
you can actually take any skills that
would be available for Open Claw and
install them in Hermes Agent. It's just
not as native. Continuing, if we look at
the native providers, this is for AI
integrations, messaging etc. Open Claw
definitely has a lot more. It's a more
mature ecosystem. Whereas with Hermes
Agent, you still can connect to pretty
much anything you would want to, but a
lot of those model connections are going
to happen through Open Router. If we
look at daily tokens, we already talked
about this, but Hermes has recently
surpassed Open Claw. And then one thing
that's super important is that Open Claw
has had a bad reputation with security.
There was a massive incident that
happened in February of 2026 where over
40,000 open claw instances were exposed
to the internet, meaning they could be
configured, changed, and were publicly
available. Whereas with Hermes, there's
been a lot less security issues. There
has still been some, but generally
speaking, people would consider Hermes
agent a little bit more secure. At this
point, it's not as big of an issue
because releases have fixed these, but
it is something that you should be aware
of. Now, in case you're not super
familiar with these tools, I do just
want to quickly cover what these
actually are. Really, the way that you
should think about and Hermes Agent is
that they're really just an LLM, so some
kind of model or brain wrapped with a
bunch of different tools. So, we have
tools, right? MCP servers, things that
can go to the internet, or go to your
Google Drive, or go to your Gmail. We
have skills. These are essentially large
markdown files that explain how to do a
task so you can do it reliably and
repeatably multiple times. We have
memory. This is so you can save, store
information, know what was talked about
in previous sessions, and improve over
time. And then we have a gateway. This
is the way in which you interact with
the model, or in this case, kind of the
agent tool, right? So, we could have
Telegram, we could have Discord, we
could have email. There's all different
kinds of things there. Now, both Open
Claw and Hermes Agent have all of these
features, and the thing that differs is
really how well they work and the way in
which they operate, which is what we're
going to dive into. With Open Claw, your
skills and your memory aren't quite as
fine-tuned as they are with Hermes.
Whereas with Hermes, the gateway isn't
quite as good as it is with Open Claw.
So, we're going to go through all of
those differences, and that will give
you the information to understand which
one you should pick. So, this leads us
nicely into what the key difference
really is here between these two tools.
Now, with Open Claw, this is really
built around a skill catalog. This means
that there's a ton of skills that have
already been written, and what you can
do is go, browse, and install them. So,
really, when you're using Open Claw,
you're going through this huge
marketplace, you're searching for
something that already exists, and
you're clicking install. Whereas with
Hermes, this is built around a
self-learning loop. What this means is
that the more you use it, the better it
gets. It remembers things about you by
default, and it will automatically
create skills based on what you're
asking it to do. So, if you just want
something really quick out of the box,
you want to use some existing skills,
it's probably easier to do that with
Open Claw. Whereas if you're planning on
using this agent for a long time, you're
going to be chatting with it a lot,
you're going to be improving what you're
doing, continuing to teach it things,
and tell it about different processes
and systems, Hermes agent is going to be
really good because it will actually get
better over time. Now, it's worth noting
that technically both of these tools can
accomplish the exact same goals, and
anything you could do with Hermes agent,
you could also do with Open Claw. It's
really just how they're set up and which
one is going to work faster for your use
case because of how it's designed. So,
keep that in mind, there's not really a
wrong decision, one is just going to be
faster to get to the end product with
based on how it's set up. Now, one thing
to keep in mind is that this catalog of
skills is not just specific to Open
Claw, you can actually take these same
skills and run them on Hermes agent, so
don't think that you can't install
pre-built skills on Hermes, you
absolutely can. It's just a little bit
more difficult to set up. Okay, so what
I'm going to do now is I'm actually
going to deploy two instances. I'm going
to deploy an Open Claw instance and a
Hermes agent instance. We're going to
give them the same tasks and I'm going
to show you what the setup looks like,
how you run them, and what the practical
difference is when you actually have
both of these agents spun up. Now, when
it comes to deploying these agents and
setting them up, you can install them on
your own computer and your own physical
hardware devices, but typically that's
not going to be recommended. That's
because you're opening this up to your
account, your network, all of your
files, and when you have an autonomous
AI agent running, it can do things that
you didn't explicitly ask it to do. If
you do get hacked or something does
occur, it's going to be a lot more
damaging on your own computer, on your
own network, than it would be if you
used a disposable device. Now, what I
typically recommend and how I set up all
of my AI agents, is using a virtual
private server. This is a server that
runs in the cloud on a company's
infrastructure. It's a lot more secure
by default than your own machine would
be. And the most important part here is
that if something goes wrong, you can
just nuke the server. You pay 5, 10, 15
bucks a month, whatever. And if
something does go wrong, all of this is
isolated on somebody else's hardware.
You can press a single button, you can
delete it, uninstall it, and stop it
from running, and do this remotely from
anywhere, and then just restart on
another VPS. And especially if you're a
beginner and you don't know a lot about
security, this is going to be a safer
option that just gives you a reset
button if something does go wrong. So,
anyways, what I'm going to do now is
deploy the two instances. Let's go
through the process. So, for all my AI
agents and virtual private servers, I
personally use Hostinger. Been using
them for years now, and they have
one-click deploy options for both. So,
I'm just on the Open Claw page, and you
can see that you can just select a plan
here, and it will deploy and set
everything up for you automatically.
Same thing with Hermes agent. What I
typically use is the KVM 2 plan when I'm
deploying this. I'll leave them both in
the description. And full transparency,
I have a long-term partnership with
Hostinger. They sponsored a bunch of
videos on this channel, and that means
that I actually have a discount code
that you can use. It's Tech With Tim.
This will give you an additional 10% off
any subscription, as long as it is 12
months or beyond. When you are going to
deploy these, I recommend that you
uncheck the ready-to-use AI. This allows
you to put in your own API keys. If you
just want it set up immediately, you
don't want to touch anything, you can
enable that. But if you want a little
bit more control, better to remove that.
Same thing on Hermes agent, I'd
recommend going with the KVM 2 plan. You
can use my discount code if you want.
And then you can deploy both of these.
It will set everything up for you, and
you will be good to go. So, let me
deploy these and show you what it looks
like. So, both of the agents have been
deployed here. Worth noting that I
didn't do any setup. I didn't install
this from the command line. You can do
that, and if you install it on your own
device manually, you will need to go
through a little bit of setup, but it's
pretty straightforward to follow
through, and you just need an API key
for the model provider that you want to
use. Now, Open Claw's UI looks something
like this. This is the main chat
interface. You can change the model. And
then Hermes looks something like this.
Now, this is the user interface. By
default, Hermes does not come with a
user interface and you need to install
it. But if you do this through
Hostinger, it will automatically set it
up for you. Now, for both of these
agents, there is a ton of configuration
you can go through to really optimize it
for your use case. I'm not going to do
all of that. I want to show you kind of
what you get out of the box. So, if we
look at the Open Claw control board, you
can see that this is, in my opinion, a
little bit more complicated. You have a
lot of configuration options. You can
kind of do everything directly here from
the user interface. You can manage
skills, agents. You can have different
nodes and different gateways. You have
obviously communication if you want to
chat through Telegram or Discord or
something like that, automation,
infrastructure, etc. Okay? And I would
say this is a little bit more kind of
developer-focused. Whereas if we look at
something like Hermes and we check the
boards, we have different tasks,
scheduled jobs. We have a Kanban board.
This will give us kind of different swim
lanes of what it is that it's working on
and we need to do. We have different
skills that are built in by default and
then we can enable or disable them. So,
it comes with all of these automatically
enabled. Open Claw has some as well. We
have the memory, which is really easy to
manage, different spaces, profiles,
to-do's, insights, and then the logs.
And this, at least from a user
perspective, is easier to work with and
manage from the beginning. Whereas Open
Claw's going to give you a lot more
controls. Now, with Hermes, you of
course can go in the settings and you
can change some stuff here. You'll
notice it's a little bit more bare-bones
than Open Claw, at least from the UI
control. So, what I want to do now is
give both of them the same task and
let's see how they perform. So, now that
we've had a look at the user interfaces,
I want to show you some of the key
differences between these tools. Keep in
mind that these are a lot more
exaggerated when you use them over long
periods of time. It's very difficult to
demo this in just three or four minutes,
but I wanted to start from a fresh
instance so you get kind of how it
works. All right, so let's go to Open
Claw. Now, one of the main differences
between these tools is skills, skill
review, and how skills are handled. Now,
with Open Claw, typically, if you want a
skill, some kind of reusable workflow,
what you're going to do is go to the
skills tab, you're going to go to where
it says Claw Hub, which should be set up
for you automatically, and you're going
to search for it. So, you might search
for something like GitHub, and you can
see there's just a ton of skills that
are going to pop up, and these are
coming from Claw Hub, where there's like
over 5,000 skills you can use. And you
can click into one, you can read what it
looks like, okay? And then you can
install the skill. I mean, this one is
super basic, but you get the idea. So,
that's typically how you would work with
skills. And then if you wanted to make
your own custom skill, you could do
that, but you would have to manually
tell the model. So, you'd say, "Hey, I
want you to make a skill to do XYZ." And
then it can make one and install it and
set it up, but it's not being handled
automatically. Whereas, when you're
using Hermes Agent, what actually
happens is it has something called a
curator. Now, this is going to be going
through your memory, your session logs,
and what you've been chatting with the
agent about, and automatically
determining whether it needs to create a
skill or not. So, if you've done
something five, six, seven, eight times,
it's going to detect, "Hey, this is
probably something I want to turn into a
skill," and it will automatically make
that file for you and just set it up so
you can reuse it. And as you use this
over time, it will automatically adjust
the skill to improve it and adjust it
based on what you're telling the agent
to do. So, if you just want to install a
skill by default, Open Claw is a little
bit easier to do that. If you want to
have your own skills that are based on
your actual workflow, Hermes will do
that for you. And if you go to the
skills tab right here, you can see
there's a bunch that are already built
in that it will use by default. If you
search for something like GitHub, you
can see it already has a bunch of them
here, and that's already installed
because that's a popular thing to do in
Hermes. And if you want to add a new
skill, it doesn't have the marketplace
by default, you can just put in your
own. So, you can say, you know, content
writer, give it a category, give it a
description, and you can just do it like
that. So, that's one of the main
differences is skills. Now, another main
difference here is memory. Both of these
tools will automatically save things to
memory for you, but the memory in Hermes
Agent is optimized significantly. It's
much faster, it's better at detecting
when it needs to write to memory, and it
can recall through more memory than
OpenClaw can. Again, you can change
things in OpenClaw to make this better,
but typically if you want kind of an
ongoing agent that improves over time,
that's why you use Hermes. So, just to
elaborate a bit on this, this is the
Curator page directly from Hermes. You
can read it if you want. What you'll
notice is that there is a background
maintenance process that's essentially
going through any of the agent created
skills, which will be created
automatically or by you manually telling
it, and it will move those skills
through an active, stale, and archived
state based on which ones are used and
how often, you know, they're being
considered. And it says that it exists
so that the skills created via these
self-improvement loop don't pile up
forever. So, that means you can keep
creating skills without getting a ton of
context bloat. It explains in depth how
it works, but that's one of the main
distinguishers between Hermes Agent. And
you'll see here that this is the
self-improvement loop that it's talking
about. So, the agent can create, update,
and delete its own skills via the skill
manage tool. This is the agent's
procedural memory. When it figures out a
non-trivial workflow, which I'll try to
demo in 1 second, it saves the approach
as a skill for future reuse, right? And
then it works together with the memory
to be able to give you a better result
and improve over time. So, let's try to
see this in action. I'm going to paste
kind of a seven-step workflow here and
see if it will automatically create the
skill. Again, sometimes it's hard when
we're just doing one prompt at a time,
but let's run that and then I'll run the
same thing in OpenClaw and see if we get
any difference. Okay, so both the tools
are finished here. If we look at Hermes
Agent, you can see that it wrote, you
know, what it needed to do, and then it
outlined the steps that it took to
complete this. And in order to test if
this created a new skill for me, what I
did is I just opened up a new
conversation session, and I said, "Hey,
run my video research brief again. I
need you to do XYZ." And then it said,
"Okay, I'm going to do this." And notice
that the first thing it did is it looked
up a skill. Now, this skill here, source
driven briefs, is one that's not built
into Hermes by default. This is one that
was actually created after we asked it
you know in the previous conversation to
create this for us. So, it generated
this automatically in the background and
then loaded this skill and used it to
make the brief again. So, that's exactly
what I'm talking about in terms of the
self-improvement. Now, with Open Claw
here, it was able to generate the brief.
What I'm going to do now is just open a
new conversation and we'll test if it
automatically made the skill. Okay, so
let's ask it to run the research video
brief again and see if we get a
response. So, you'll see right now if we
just look through the output, there's
nothing related to any skills and while
it is able to search through the memory,
which we can see here and find the
response, it's a lot less efficient, it
takes longer, and it's not using that
skill. So, now if it ever forgets that
memory loaded in context, it's not going
to be able to give us the response. And
that's really the key difference here
between Hermes and Open Claw, how the
memory is managed and how the skills are
automatically handled and produced.
Hopefully, that makes sense to you. Now,
let's talk about a few other
differences. So, at this point, you're
probably saying, "Okay, well, I'm just
going to use Hermes agent, right?"
Because it seems like it's better. Now,
for most of you, that's the correct
choice. Hermes agent is better as more
of a personal assistant or something
that you chat with a lot. Now, I will
say that one of the things that does
give Open Claw a little bit of an edge
and probably the only reason I would use
it now in 2026 is its gateway management
and advanced configuration. So, let's
say that you want to have multiple
people from different areas chatting
with your bot. Maybe you want it to be
customer facing, maybe you want to have
different people in your organization
using it. In my experience, it's easier
to set up multiple gateways with Open
Claw and route them into different
agents with shared memory than it is to
do that with Hermes. Then, to go back to
my presentation to explain this. So, for
example, maybe you have Telegram users,
Discord users, you know, website widget,
WhatsApp, Line, you can have different
gateways set up in Open Claw that can
handle that. You can also do this in
Hermes Agent, but again, in my
experience, it's a little bit easier and
more intuitive inside of Open Claw. So,
that's one reason why you might want to
use this is if you have different types
of avatars or people using it. If you're
just a single user, you're probably
going to go with Hermes. Now, you're
going to notice that the main gap here
is the repetitive work. We already saw
this a little bit with Open Claw,
everything that you're doing is pretty
much manual. You need to tell it to make
a skill, you need to know that it needs
to optimize this. Whereas with Hermes,
it's doing all of that in the background
for you. Now, when you have this set up,
it actually means that your agent gets
cheaper to run over time because it's
learning how to do things, and it
doesn't need to rediscover that. You saw
that when we wanted to remake the brief,
it just pulled the skill. It was already
there. It was created one time. Whereas
Open Claw, anytime we wanted to do that,
if we didn't manually tell it to make
the skill, it needs to figure this out
again. It needs to search the memory, go
through the tools, and it doesn't have
that baked in like Hermes Agent does,
which means it can be very expensive to
run continuously. Now, continuing here,
the bigger ecosystem also leads to a
bigger target. So, with Open Claw, if
you're installing a ton of different
skills from the Claw Hub, a lot of these
could have security vulnerabilities, and
this is exactly what we saw back in
February where people had all of these
skills baked in or they've set up things
incorrectly where they're exposed on the
web. Whereas with Hermes, it's a lot
smaller surface, you're not pulling in
all of this stuff externally, which
leads to it being typically a little bit
more secure. Now, let's keep going, and
let's just have a look at a side-by-side
comparison. So, when we talk about cost,
typically going to be a bit more
expensive with Open Claw on the same
tasks. Whereas with Hermes, it optimizes
and gets better over time. In terms of
the setup, Open Claw is one click, same
with Hermes. However, it It be a little
bit more advanced to set up, especially
if we get into the gateway stuff. You
saw the UI is not quite as friendly,
whereas with Hermes, it's pretty much
just there, ready to go, and you don't
really need to tweak anything. In terms
of capability, there is more skills
definitely with OpenClaw. You have that
multi-gateway support, you have a ton of
different providers, so maybe you have a
little bit more advanced capability, but
with Hermes, you have the learning loop,
you have the memory, and it can also run
the same OpenClaw skills. You can just
pull them in and manually create them
there. Now, OpenClaw is going to be best
for things that are customer-facing,
multi-channel, a lot more advanced,
where you want to kind of get your hands
dirty, whereas Hermes is significantly
better as a daily driver, anything that
repeats or that you're going to be
chatting with a lot. So, in most cases,
you're going to go with Hermes, but if
for some reason you're a more advanced
user, you have kind of this special use
case, then OpenClaw can be considered.
But, that's pretty much the conclusion,
guys. I would almost always go with
Hermes in 2026, but I wanted to show you
why that's the case, that you have some
evidence to back up that decision, and
you know which is best for you. So, I'm
going to wrap up the video here. If you
enjoyed, make sure to leave a like,
subscribe, and I will see you in the
next one.
>> [music]